<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="120912">
 <algorithm name="AAMatching" version="120912">
  <results date="2012-09-12-16:55:50.170000" time="1347440150.17"/>
  <instituitions>
   <instituition>Department of Computer Science, University of Manitoba, Winnipeg, Canada</instituition>
   <instituition>Department of Computer Science, Ryerson University, Toronto, Canada</instituition>
  </instituitions>
  <authors>
   <author>
    <fullname source="parscit">Saeed Rashwand</fullname>
    <institutions>
     <instituition>Department of Computer Science, University of Manitoba, Winnipeg, Canada</instituition>
    </institutions>
   </author>
   <author>
    <fullname source="parscit">Jelena MiÅ¡iÄ?</fullname>
    <institutions>
     <instituition>Department of Computer Science, Ryerson University, Toronto, Canada</instituition>
    </institutions>
   </author>
  </authors>
 </algorithm>
 <algorithm name="SectLabel">
  <variant confidence="1.0" no="0">
   <title confidence="1.0">Stable operation of IEEE 802.11e EDCA: Interaction between offered load and MAC parameters</title>
   <author confidence="1.0">Saeed Rashwand</author>
   <affiliation confidence="1.0">Department of Computer Science, University of Manitoba, Winnipeg, Canada</affiliation>
   <email confidence="1.0">rashwand@cs.umanitoba.ca</email>
   <author confidence="1.0">Jelena MiÅ¡iÄ?</author>
   <affiliation confidence="1.0">Department of Computer Science, Ryerson University, Toronto, Canada</affiliation>
   <sectionHeader confidence="1.0" genericHeader="abstract">Abstract</sectionHeader>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">In this paper, we study impacts of TXOP allocation and AIFS parameter on one hop IEEE 802.11e EDCA network under varying offered load. Offered load is modified by changing the parameters of arrival process and node populations. Arrival process is varied by altering burst size distribution, mean burst size, frame size, and arrival rates. We investigate the effects of the offered load parameters on the network stability and non-saturation boundaries of IEEE 802.11e EDCA. Our results show interaction of offered load and MAC parameters. The results suggest the range of network parameters which preserve network stability and still achieve QoS differentiation.</bodyText>
   <sectionHeader confidence="1.0" genericheader="introduction">1 Introduction</sectionHeader>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">Due to low cost and simplicity in deployment, the IEEE 802.11-based wireless LANs are considered as the de facto standard for providing wireless network access. The IEEE 802.11 Medium Access Control (MAC) introduces two main access functions for wireless networks. Point Coordination Function (PCF) is the contention free medium access mechanism. Distributed Coordination Function (DCF) is the contention-based mechanism of the standard which is simple to implement. This function is currently the most common access control mechanism for wireless networks which is implemented in most commercial products. However, the service to the data frames in the DCF is best effort. That is, it provides no quality of service to guarantee delay or throughput. As a result, real-time flows may experience arbitrary delays when the network load is high due to the CSMA/CA mechanism.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">To improve the IEEE 802.11 standard to support quality of service in wireless network, the IEEE 802.11 working group introduced IEEE 802.11e standard to differentiate the traffic flows in the network [1] . The IEEE 802.11e standard specifies a new medium access coordination function called Hybrid Coordination Function (HCF) which is only usable in QoS network configurations. The contention-based channel access method of HCF function is called Enhanced Distributed Channel Access (EDCA).</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">The EDCA mechanism provides differentiated, distributed access to the wireless medium for stations based on eight user priorities. In fact, the packets from the upper layer are marked according to these priorities and are passed to the MAC layer. The user priorities are mapped into four Access Categories, AC k , k = 0, â?¦ , 3, in the MAC layer. AC 0 is the lowest priority class while AC 3 is the highest priority class. EDCA differentiate the traffic according to the AC. The differentiation is achieved by varying the following four differentiation parameters; Amount of time a station senses the channel to be idle before backoff or transmission (Arbitrary Inter-Frame Space - AIFS), the length of contention window for backoff (minimum and maximum Contention Windows â?? CW min and CW max ), and the duration a station may transmit after it acquires the channel (Transmission Opportunity â?? TXOP).</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">Each AC has its own queue and channel access differentiation parameters. In fact, EDCA is a contention-based mechanism that provides lower channel access delay to higher priority classes. However, because the EDCA mechanism introduces a probabilistic approach for accessing the medium it cannot provide hard QoS guarantees such as minimum throughput value or strict delay bound even for the highest priority class.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">According to the standard, an AC could not decrease its backoff counter and send its frame before the end of its AIFS even if the channel is idle. Therefore, because the higher priority classes often have the lower AIFS value they decrease their backoff counters relatively faster and transmit more frames. The duration of AIFS k is equal to SIFS + AIFSN k SlotTime , k = 0, 1, 2, 3, where the value of AIFSN k shall be greater than or equal to 2. The timing diagram which shows priority among access categories according to their AIFS values is shown in Fig. 1 . It is expected that smaller AIFS value, minimum and maximum contention window sizes improve the channel access and prioritize the AC to transmit.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">In the recent years, a large body of work has appeared in the literature to investigate performance of IEEE 802.11e EDCA. It includes analytical and simulation models to study the behavior of the standard to understand the impacts of the differentiation parameters on network performance and its QoS provision for different priority classes. The huge part of the work presented in this area is to introduce analytical models to evaluate performance of IEEE 802.11e EDCA. However, due to very high complexity of presenting an analytical model which addresses all the features and details of the standard all the proposed analytical models are not precise and ignore some important specifications of the standard to simplify the modelling. Several analytical models have been proposed that mostly extend the Bianchiâ??s two dimensional Markov chain model for IEEE 802.11 DCF to take into account different differentiation parameters of IEEE 802.11e EDCA. The analytical models are generally separated to those which consider saturation condition and those which address non-saturation condition. In saturation condition there is always at least one data frame in the queue waiting to be served.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">Because considering saturation condition makes the model much simpler researchers have mainly focused on the saturation analysis of IEEE 802.11e EDCA. This assumption simplifies the model because the traffic characteristics can be neglected. Recently, saturation regime has been studied in [2â??8] . All the models except the one in [6] set the TXOP parameter to 0 so that all the stations are allowed to transmit just one data frame in case of winning the medium. In addition, all the models consider ideal channel condition, which is an unreal assumption. Therefore, the models do not reflect the real network situation.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">Compared to saturation condition, there are few works that evaluate the IEEE 802.11e EDCA under non-saturation condition. In [9,10] , authors analyzed IEEE 802.11e under non-saturation condition. However, their models have inaccuracies related to backoff countdown and ignore TXOP. In [11] , the authors proposed a three dimensional Markov chain that for the first time includes TXOP limit. However, the model does not include AIFS countdown. In [12] , Abu-Sharkh and Tewfik proposed a complex multi-dimensional Markov chain which covers important features of IEEE 802.11e EDCA under finite load. Though their model covers important features of IEEE 802.11e EDCA, it includes some inaccuracies. The main inaccuracy is related to the AIFS sensing period. Therefore, the suggested models for non-saturation condition are imprecise. Thus, more works are still required to study behavior of the IEEE 802.11e EDCA standard more precisely.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">When the traffic increases, the network moves from non-saturation regime to saturation one. If a station is under saturation condition its mean arrival rate is larger than its average transmission rate. Thus, the buffer overflow may occur for the station that makes the network unstable. Hence, if the network has to operate in a stable regime, the frame arrival rate should not exceed the non-saturation boundaries for the lowest priority class. However, because the frame arrival rate is dependent on the applications, stability of the network should be preserved by controlling other parameters in the network such as the node populations for the traffic classes. In this paper, we perform an extensive simulation study to investigate transition from the non-saturation regime to the saturation. We study the impacts of bursty traffic, different arrival rates of access categories, frame sizes, node populations, TXOP values, and AIFS parameter on performance of a single hop wireless network based on the IEEE 802.11e EDCA standard.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">The paper is organized as follows: Section 2 gives more details about the simulation setup. In Section 3 , effects of the mentioned parameters on the network performance are studied. In this section, normalized throughput, mean data frame access delay, average time between two successive TXOP accesses, success probability, and mean number of successfully transmitted frames during a TXOP period of ACs are investigated. Finally, Section 4 concludes the paper and highlights some avenues for future research.</bodyText>
   <sectionHeader confidence="1.0" genericheader="method">2 Simulation setup</sectionHeader>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">In this work, we use OPNET simulator [13] for evaluating the IEEE 802.11e EDCA. In the simulation we consider four ACs. For focusing on the differentiation parameters and achieving clearer results we consider that each station has exactly one queue with a specific AC. We assume a single hop ad-hoc network with n k nodes transmitting frames from traffic class k for which the frame destination is chosen randomly. We suppose five stations from every access category unless otherwise mentioned. The transmission rate is set to 2 Mbps. According to the standard the header fields are transmitted at 1 Mbps. Frame size excluding the MAC and PHY headers is set to 100 B, except the case that we investigate the effects of frame size on the network performance in which we consider frames of 500 B payload size too. In the simulation we employ RTS/CTS mechanism for transmission of all frames by all the stations. Therefore, collision can occur only for RTS frames. The buffer size of every station is set to 32 KB. Therefore, the buffer overflow occurs in saturation condition for all the stations and the extra frames are dropped.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">In our work, we keep two differentiation parameters CW min and CW max constant. The AIFS k values are also identical and constant throughout the paper, except the section that we study effects of different arrival rates for different access categories. We adopt AIFSN 3 = 2, AIFSN 2 = 3, AIFSN 1 = 5, and AIFSN 0 = 7 throughout the study except the mentioned section. The values CW min = 31 and CW max = 511 are selected for all the ACs. Thus, number of backoff phases is controlled with m k = 4, k = 0, â?¦ , 3. In addition, Short Retry Limit and Long Retry Limit are both set to 7. The Bit Error Rate ( ber ) is set to 2 Ã? 10 â??5 . Frames from traffic class k arrive to the queue according to the Poisson process with rate of Î» k . Note that in all the plots solid , dotted , dashed , and dash â?? dotted lines represent the corresponding values for AC 0 , AC 1 , AC 2 , and AC 3 , respectively.</bodyText>
   <sectionHeader confidence="1.0" genericheader="method">3 Performance analysis</sectionHeader>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">In our experiments we measure and discuss following network descriptors: â?¢ Normalized throughput for access category of k is defined as the fraction of time in which the channel is used to transmit class k frames successfully. â?¢ Mean frame access delay is defined as the time interval between the instant that the frame arrives to the queue and the time when the frame is successfully acknowledged by the receiver. That is, the delay includes queueing and medium access delays at the source MAC, successfully reception of the frame by the receiver and successfully reception of the ACK frame, and all the unsuccessful transmissions of the frame. â?¢ Average time between two successive TXOP accesses by a station includes the period of time that the station has uninterrupted access to the medium, the contention period for winning the TXOP and the probable idle period when the queue is empty. We refer to it as the service period. â?¢ According to the standard, the station wins a TXOP period if it successfully transmits an RTS frame and receives the CTS frame. Then it is allowed to transmit during TXOP period without interruption. Success probability of acquiring TXOP is defined as number of successful TXOP accesses over number of attempts. â?¢ The last performance descriptor is mean number of successfully transmitted frames during a TXOP period.</bodyText>
   <subSectionHeader confidence="1.0">3.1 Impacts of burst arrival on network performance</subSectionHeader>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">In the first experiment we consider Poisson arrival of frame bursts. Burst size is either geometrically distributed or constant. In this section, we investigate how bursty arrival affects the network performance. In addition, we study how selecting appropriate TXOP differentiation parameter improves the performance. We consider three different scenarios, as shown in Table 1 to achieve our purpose. In the first two scenarios we suppose that the burst size is geometrically distributed with parameter p = 0.2. Thus, the mean and the variance of the burst sizes are equal to 5 and 20, respectively. In the last scenario in this section we assume that the burst size is constant which is equal to 5.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">For the first scenario, we set the TXOP value to 0 for all the ACs so that the station which wins the medium is allowed to transmit just one data frame. However, for the second and third scenarios we set the TXOP value to 6000 Î¼s for all the access categories which is the required transmission time for 5 data frames.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">Fig. 2 aâ??c depict the normalized throughput for the three mentioned scenarios. It is clear that if the TXOP value is set in a way that a TXOP period can include transmission of the whole burst of data frames the normalized throughput of all the access categories, as a result the whole network, is considerably improved. In addition, this extends the stability region of the network. A station of access category k enters into unstable region when its normalized throughput does not increase when the data frame arrival rate increases. However, the network enters into unstable region when the lowest priority stations enter into the unstable region. In the first scenario where the stations can transmit just one frame in a TXOP period the point that the lowest priority class enters into saturation region is about 24 fps (4.8 burst arrivals per second in average). However, this value is 37 fps (7.4 burst arrivals per second in average) in the second scenario.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">Note that when the burst size is constant and equal to 5, the normalized throughput is slightly improved compared to the case where the burst size is geometrically distributed with the same mean. The reason is the relatively large variance of the geometric distribution. Therefore, it is less likely that a TXOP period could cover transmission of the whole burst of data frames where arrive geometrically distributed. In addition, because the channel is noisy there is a small probability that the whole burst of size five could not be transmitted at once. This affects the performance of the network during non-saturation regime because the stations have to compete for the medium to transmit the failed transmitted data frames.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">Fig. 2 dâ??f shows the mean access delay of the data frames which arrive in burst. Considering the fixed size of the buffer of the stations the huge improvement in the end to end delay of the data frames occurs if the whole burst is transmitted during the TXOP period as depicted in the plots.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">Fig. 3 aâ??c depict the average service period length for all the access categories. Plot (a) indicates that when the TXOP value is 0 the average interval length is around 40 ms at the end of stability region of the network. It indicates that the stations require more frequently to access the TXOP period. In addition, for a low load the time is less than 200 ms. However, plot (b) shows a large decrease in the number of requests for accessing the medium. For a low load the interval length is more than 200 while the network is in stable region yet. Finally, plot (c) indicates that if the TXOP period covers the whole burst of the data frames the number of access requests is even smaller than that of the previous case where the standard deviation of the burst size is rather large. Note that during saturation region there is not a significant difference between the average interval length of the second and the third scenarios.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">Fig. 3 dâ??f shows the success probability of accessing TXOP for all the access categories for the three scenarios. Note that in the first scenario success probability for all the access categories is larger than 90% if the arrival rate is less than 19 fps. However, the numbers for the other two scenarios are equal to 28 fps and 33 fps. Note that when the network is saturated for all the access categories there is no difference among all the cases regarding the probability of successful access to the medium.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">Finally, Fig. 3 gâ??i depict the number of successfully transmitted frames during TXOP period for all the access categories. When the TXOP value is 0 the number of successfully transmitted frames is approximately 0.97 due to the noisy channel. Because the packet error rate throughout the paper is fixed this number is constant when the TXOP is set to 0. During the stable region of the network for the second scenario when the burst size is geometrically distributed the number of successfully transmitted frames during TXOP period is smaller than the case when the burst size is constant. Especially when the load is low (less than 30 fps) this number is around 3.3 frames per TXOP period in average for the second scenario compared to 4.25 frames per second in average for the third scenario. This justifies the smaller number of medium access requests for the third scenario where most likely the whole burst is serviced during a TXOP period.</bodyText>
   <subSectionHeader confidence="1.0">3.2 Different frame arrival rates for ACs</subSectionHeader>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">In this section, we study how different frame arrival rates for four access categories affects the performance of the network. Given different frame arrival rates of ACs we investigate how adopting differentiation parameters could improve the network performance.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">Throughout this section, we assume that the frame arrival rates for different access categories have the ratios of 2, 4, 7, and 10 for AC 0 , AC 1 , AC 2 , and AC 3 , respectively. For instance, given number of 5 the data frame arrival rates of AC 0 , AC 1 , AC 2 , and AC 3 are equal to 10, 20, 35, and 50 frames per second, respectively. However, if we assume the number of 10 the data frame arrival rates of AC 0 , AC 1 , AC 2 , and AC 3 are equal to 20, 40, 70, and 100 frames per second, respectively.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">We study four different scenarios during this section, as shown in Table 2 . For the first two scenarios, we apply prioritization among the access categories through different AIFS values. We set the arbitrary inter-frame space parameter for different access categories to AIFSN 0 = 7, AIFSN 1 = 5, AIFSN 2 = 3, and AIFSN 3 = 2, as before. However, all the AC s have the same TXOP values.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">In the first scenario, we set TXOP to 0 for all the access categories. That is, wining the wireless medium all the stations are allowed to transmit just one data frame on the medium. For the second scenario, the TXOP value is set to 11,100Î¼s for all the access categories which is the required transmission time for 10 data frames on the medium. In fact, this scenarios help to find out how TXOP value affects the non-saturation regions of the network when the frame arrival rates of AC s are not identical.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">In the next two scenarios in this section, we prioritize the access categories through TXOP k values instead of AIFS k differentiation parameter. That is, we assume that all the stations of any access category in the network have the same AIFS value where AIFSN k = 2, k = 0, â?¦ , 3. We set the Transmission Opportunities for different access categories to TXOP 0 = 2750 Î¼s, TXOP 1 = 4900 Î¼s, TXOP 2 = 8000 Î¼s, and TXOP 3 = 11,100 Î¼s which are the required transmission time for 2, 4, 7, and 10 data frames, respectively.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">In the third scenario, we assume that the frames arrive in non-bursty traffic. However, in the last scenario the data frames arrive in burst where the burst size is constant. The burst size for the access categories AC 0 , AC 1 , AC 2 , and AC 3 are set to 2, 4, 7, and 10 frames, respectively. Note that the burst size corresponds to the frame arrival rate ratios for different access categories in the first three scenarios of this section. That is, in the last scenario for a given number of 5 the burst arrival rates for all the access categories are equal to 5 arrivals per second.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">Note that in Figs. 4 and 8 the frame arrival rate equals to multiplication of the number shown in the x -axis and the Î» ratio or the burst size if applicable. For instance, in Fig. 4 a the saturation region for the lowest priority class starts when its frame arrival rate is equal to 8 = 2 * 4 while the frame arrival rates at the same point for AC 1 , AC 2 and AC 3 are equal to 16, 28, and 40 frames per second, respectively.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">Fig. 4 indicates that the TXOP limit growth extends the non-saturation regions for all the AC s. In addition, increasing the TXOP value helps the medium to be more utilized resulting higher normalized throughput for all the access categories. Clearly, increasing TXOP value from the time for transmission of one frame to the time for transmission of 10 frames improves the total normalized throughput of the network from approximately 19% to around 34% under saturation condition. Note that an important reason for the low normalized throughput is the small frame size. In the next section, we will show that the network normalized throughput is improved when the frame size increases. In addition, having RTS/CTS mechanism and high traffic in the network are other reasons for the low normalized throughput for the network.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">Fig. 4 c and d clearly indicate how different TXOP values can play the same role of AIFS k for differentiating the access categories. In fact, assigning suitable TXOP values to different access categories can dramatically improve the network performance. In addition, these plots indicate that in case of having burst arrival with constant burst sizes the network performance is improved if the TXOP value for AC s are assigned according to the burst size compared to the non-bursty frame arrival. In fact, it extends the non-saturation regions to some extent.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">Fig. 5 aâ??d also shows the improvement of packet access delay when the TXOP value increases. It seems that if the frame arrival rates to stations of different AC s are different assigning suitable TXOP values is an efficient tool to improve performance of the network without engaging in the other differentiation parameters.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">Fig. 6 depicts the average service period. When TXOP limit is increased under non-saturation condition the higher priority classes compete less for the medium which improves the network performance. Note that this descriptor is equal for all the AC s when the frames arrive in burst and the required time is assigned to every station to transmits the whole burst in a TXOP period. This helps the stations to improve the access delay of the frames and less collision as a result of less attempt for the medium. A big difference between the first two plots and the next two plots of Fig. 6 is the shape of the plots during saturation region. This clearly shows that all the stations in the network have the same probability of winning the medium.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">Fig. 7 shows how success probability of winning the access to TXOP period varies for the mentioned scenarios. It is totally clear how TXOP growth pushes the boundaries between saturation and non-saturation regions. In case of having different values for TXOP for different access categories, the probability of success during the non-saturation region considerably increases when the frames arrive in burst. The reason is the smaller competition for accessing the medium.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">Fig. 8 depicts the mean number of successfully transmitted frames during the acquired TXOP period. Fig. 8 a indicates that because the frames arrive in non-burst mode during non saturation region the TXOP period is underutilized. However, the TXOP utilization dramatically increases when the network reaches the saturation boundaries. Note that TXOP value allows the stations to transmit up to 10 frames, but during non-saturation region the actual number of transmitted frames is much lower that forces the stations to compete for the medium as soon as a frame arrives. However, Fig. 8 c shows that when the frames arrive in burst the TXOP period is much more utilized which decreases the contention on the medium.</bodyText>
   <subSectionHeader confidence="1.0">3.3 Impacts of frame size on network performance</subSectionHeader>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">In this section we investigate how the frame size affects the performance measures including the normalized throughput of a network. Since the channel is noisy frame error rate increases with frame size. For studying the effect of the frame size, we compare the performance measures for the case when the size of frame payload is 100 B and the case when the size is 500 B (see Table 3 ). We assume that every station which wins the medium is allowed to transmit just one data frame regardless of the frame size. That is, the TXOP value is set to 0 for all the access categories .</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">Fig. 4 e and f clearly prove that increasing the frame size dramatically improves the total normalized throughput of the network and also that of all the access categories. In fact, in case of 100 B payload size the network enters into unstable situation at around 24 fps. However, when the payload size is 500 B the network instability occurs when the arrival rate is approximately 13 frames per second. That is, in the first case, under stable condition all the stations in the network can transmit up to 2400 B per second. However, this value is 6500 B per second when the payload size is 500 B. Therefore, during stable region of the network the throughput considerably increases for all the access categories.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">Fig. 5 e and f indicate how the mean frame access delay is changed when the frame size increases. during saturation region when there are always some frames in the queue waiting to be served, in case of larger payload size the mean access delay for all the access categories is less than half of the delay for the case when the payload size is 100 B. In addition, as expected the average time between two TXOP accesses in order for the case when the payload size is 500 B is larger than that of when the fram payload size is 100 B, as shown in Fig. 6 e and f. The reason is that all the stations spend more time for transmission of a single frame during TXOP period.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">Finally, Fig. 7 e and f shows the success probability of winning the TXOP period. These plots indicate that increasing the packet size decreases the stable region of the network with respect to frame arrival rate. In fact, the network enters into non-stable region with respect to the frame arrival rate sooner for larger frame sizes.</bodyText>
   <subSectionHeader confidence="1.0">3.4 Impacts of node populations on network performance</subSectionHeader>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">In this section, we examine how node populations of different ACs affect the normalized throughput acquired by every AC. The normalized throughput plots clearly show non-saturation regions and in fact non-saturation boundaries for all the access categories. Fig. 9 aâ??c depict the normalized throughput values for different scenarios. Each plot indicates three different scenarios. That is, each plot includes the normalized throughput values for all the considered traffic rates of all the access categories given fixed numbers of stations of access categories AC 0 , AC 1 and AC 2 , fixed TXOP value but different number of stations of AC 3 (2, 5, and 8), as shown in Table 4 . We assume that TXOP = 3800 Î¼s for all the ACs which is the required transmission time for three data frames.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">The standard is ambiguous regarding the error recovery during TXOP period. In fact, the standard mentions that the stations may recover its uninterrupted access to the medium during the TXOP period in the case that the transmitted data frame is failed because of noise on the channel. Thus, there can be two different approaches to recover the error or not. In the previous sections, we assumed that all the stations in the network recover their error by continuing the transmission during TXOP period if there is enough time. However, in this section we suppose that if there is transmission failure during the TXOP period the medium becomes idle and the station stops its transmission. Results indicate that the latter approach degrades the network performance because of lower utilization of TXOP period.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">In order to study the effects of node populations in the network on saturation regions of the network, we employ nine different scenarios. In the all cases, we consider five stations of AC 0 and AC 1 . Numbers of stations of AC 2 and AC 3 are set to 2, 5, or 8. Like before, in all the plots solid , dotted , dashed , and dash â?? dotted lines represent the corresponding values for AC 0 , AC 1 , AC 2 , and AC 3 , respectively. In addition, the different thickness of the lines indicates different scenarios. Each plot includes the values from three different scenarios that are related to the number of stations of the highest AC. The thickness of the plots increases when number of stations of AC 3 changes from 2 to 5 and then 8. In this section, we set CW min = 31 and CW max = 1023 for all the access categories. That is, number of backoff phases for all the ACs is equal to m k = 5. In addition, in this part Long Retry and Short Retry Limits are both set to 5.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">We note that, as the traffic increases, the network moves through linear (non-saturation) regime, transition to saturation regime. In Fig. 9 a numbers of stations of AC 0 , AC 1 and AC 2 are 5, 5 and 2, respectively. Given 2 stations of AC 3 , the lowest priority AC transits from non-saturation regime to saturation one where the arrival rate is about 43 fps. In this case, saturation occurs at loads of 60, 85 and 120 fps for traffic classes 1, 2, and 3, respectively. However, 36 and 30 fps are the transition points from non-saturation to saturation regime when there are 5 and 8 stations of AC 3 . Therefore, as plots indicate increase of numbers of stations in the access categories strongly affect the saturation region. Although at the previously mentioned point the other ACs except the lowest priority AC are still in their non-saturation regions, the network operates in unstable condition.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">In Fig. 9 b number of stations in each of AC 0 , AC 1 and AC 2 is 5. The transition points from the non-saturation region to saturation one for the lowest priority traffic class occur at loads of 36, 30, and 25 fps when number of highest priority AC nodes is 2, 5, and 8, respectively. Beyond the rates the network enters unstable saturated situation, though some ACs may still be in non-saturated situation.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">In Fig. 9 c, there are 5, 5, and 8-nodes of AC 0 , AC 1 and AC 2 , respectively. In this case, the network enters saturation region at loads of 30, 25, and 22 fps when number of stations of AC 3 is equal to 2, 5, and 8, respectively.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">Fig. 9 dâ??f depict the mean access delay of frames for all the ACs considering different node populations. The mean access delay plots clearly indicate the non-saturation and saturation regions for all the ACs in different scenarios. For the lowest priority access category the mean packet access delay may be as high as 30 s given the mentioned differentiation parameters. These stations may strongly suffer from network traffic congestion. Therefore, the node populations and TXOP limits should be controlled to preserve network stability and provide some guarantees for throughput and access delay for all the traffic classes.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">Fig. 10 aâ??c represent the average interval period between two successive successfully acquired TXOP. During the non-saturation region of the station, increase of arrival rate decreases the average service period because the idle period is diminished. When the station enters the saturation region the service period increases as it is expected. Fig. 10 aâ??c plots clearly indicate how the low priority AC suffers from saturation condition regarding the service period, inasmuch as the service period may change from around 50 ms to about 330 ms when frame arrival rate increases by about 20 fps.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">Fig. 10 dâ??f present the success probability of accessing TXOP of all the ACs for different node populations. For all the scenarios the success probability of acquiring TXOP degrades when packet arrival rate grows. For instance, based on Fig. 10 e success probability of acquiring TXOP for the lowest priority class is around 90% when it enters its saturation region (25, 30, or 36 fps arrival rate) while that probability is approximately 60% when the arrival rate is increased by about 10 fps. Network traffic growth decreases success probability of accessing TXOP with high slopes until all the stations in the network operate under saturation condition. As it is expected increasing network traffic diminishes probability of successfully transmission of RTS and CTS control frames because of the increased contention. Node populations clearly affect the success probability of transmission for contending nodes.</bodyText>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">Finally, Fig. 10 gâ??i represent mean number of transmitted frames during the TXOP period. These plots verify the above discussion about the stability and instability regions of the network and how it is affected by the node populations in the network.</bodyText>
   <sectionHeader confidence="1.0" genericheader="conclusions">4 Conclusion</sectionHeader>
   <bodyText confidence="1.0">In this paper, we investigated the effects of burst arrival, different arrival rates of access categories, frame size, node populations of ACs and TXOP limits on performance of a single hop network working based on IEEE 802.11e EDCA. The results indicated that if the data frames arrive in burst adopting value of TXOP which more likely covers transmission of the whole burst the network performance is considerably improved. We discovered that the reason is decrease of the contention during non-saturation region. Moreover, in case of having different arrival rates for the access categories adopting an appropriate TXOP value can significantly improve the network performance. In addition, the results show that having higher frame sizes enhances the total normalized throughput of the network for all the access categories. However, the mean access delay of the frames increases due to longer frame transmission time and increased frame error rate. We showed that growth of number of stations, specially higher priority ones, strongly reduces non-saturation regions. Therefore, TXOP values, frame sizes, and especially the number of nodes in each class are suitable controlling tools for keeping the network in a stable condition when network load grows. In fact, we came to conclusion that adopting suitable values for TXOP limits improves the QoS provided to all the ACs in the network. The results from this paper clearly show how admission control by the Access Point (AP) can improve the network stability by controlling the parameters of offered load and the EDCA differentiation parameters.</bodyText>
   <sectionHeader confidence="1.0" genericHeader="references">References</sectionHeader>
   <reference confidence="1.0">
IEEE 802.11, IEEE Standard for Information Technology Telecommunications and Information Exchange Between Systems Local and Metropolitan area Networks Specific Requirements. Part 11: Wireless LAN Medium Access Control (MAC) and Physical Layer (PHY) Specifications, 2007.
J. Hui, M. Devetsikiotis, A unified model for the performance analysis of IEEE 802.11e wireless LANs, IEEE Transactions on Communications, 2005
Z. Tao, S. Panwar, Throughput and delay analysis for the IEEE 802.11e enhanced distributed channel access, IEEE Transactions on Communications, 2006
H. Wu, X. Wang, Q. Zhang, X. Shen, IEEE 802.11e enhanced distributed channel access (EDCA) throughput analysis, in: Proceedings of IEEE International Conference on Communications (ICCâ??06), vol. 1, 2006, pp. 223â??228.
Y. Yan, C. Pan, An improved analytical model for IEEE802.11e enhanced distributed channel access, in: Proceedings of International Symposium on Information Technology Convergence (ISITCâ??07), vol. 1, 2007, pp. 135â??142.
N.C. Taher, Y.G. Doudane, B. ElHassan, A complete and accurate analytical model for IEEE 802.11e EDCA under saturation conditions, in: Proceedings of ACS/IEEE AICCSA, vol. 1, May 2009, pp. 800â??807.
J.Y. Lee, H.S. Lee, A performance analysis model for IEEE 802.11e EDCA under saturation condition, IEEE Transactions on Communications, 2009
I. Inan, F. Keceli, E. Ayanoglu, Saturation throughput analysis of the 802.11e enhanced distributed channel access function, in: Proceedings of IEEE International Conference on Communications (ICCâ??07), vol. 1, 2007, pp. 409â??414.
P.E. Engelstad, O.N. Osterbo, Analysis of the total delay of the IEEE 802.11e EDCA and 802.11 DCF, in: Proceedings of IEEE International Conference on Communications (ICC â??06), vol. 2, 2006, pp. 552â??559.
P.E. Engelstad, O.N. Osterbo, Queueing delay analysis of IEEE 802.11e EDCA, in: Proceedings of Wireless On demand Network Systems and Services (Wonsâ??06), vol. 1, 2006, pp. 123â??133.
I. Inan, F. Keceli, E. Ayanoglu, Modeling the 802.11e enhanced distributed channel access function, in: Proceedings of IEEE Global Telecommunications Conference (Globecom07), vol. 1, 2007, pp. 2546â??2551.
O.M.F. Abu-Sharkh, A.H. Tewfik, Toward accurate modeling of the IEEE 802.11e EDCA under finite load and error-prone channel, IEEE Transactions on Wireless Communications, 2008
OPNET Technologies, Inc., OPNET Modeler, Bethesda, MD, 2009.</reference>
  </variant>
 </algorithm>
</algorithms>